<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY filename "draft-ietf-manet-dlep-credit-flow-control-18">
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="std"
     ipr="trust200902"
     docName="&filename;"
     obsoletes="" updates=""
     submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en"
     tocInclude="true"
     symRefs="true" sortRefs="true"
     version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.19.4 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="DLEP Credit-Based Flow Control">
  Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP) Credit-Based Flow Control Messages and Data Items</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-manet-dlep-credit-flow-control-18"/>
    <author initials="B." surname="Cheng" fullname="Bow-Nan Cheng">
      <organization>MIT Lincoln Laboratory</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</street>
          <street>244 Wood Street</street>
          <city>Lexington</city>
          <region>MA</region>
          <code>02421-6426</code>
        </postal>
        <email>bcheng@ll.mit.edu</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="D." surname="Wiggins" fullname="David Wiggins">
      <address>
        <email>david@none.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Stan Ratliff" initials="S." surname="Ratliff">
      <address>
        <email>stan@none.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="L." surname="Berger" fullname="Lou Berger">
      <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>lberger@labn.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author role="editor" initials="E." surname="Kinzie" fullname="Eric Kinzie">
      <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>ekinzie@labn.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

   <date/>
   <abstract>
     <t>
     This document defines new Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP)
     Data Items that are used to support credit-based flow control.
     Credit window control is used to regulate when data may be sent to
     an associated virtual or physical queue.  The Data Items are
     extensible and reusable.
     </t>
   </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
    <section anchor="sec-1" numbered="true">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
      The Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP), defined in <xref target="RFC8175" format="default"/>, provides the exchange of link related
      control information between DLEP peers.  DLEP peers are comprised
      of a modem and a router.  DLEP defines a base set of mechanisms as
      well as support for future extensions.  DLEP defines Data Items
      which are sets of information that can be reused in DLEP
      messaging.
      The DLEP specification does not include any flow
      identification beyond DLEP endpoints nor flow control capability.
      There are various flow control techniques theoretically possible
      with DLEP.  For example, a credit-window scheme for
      destination-specific flow control which provides aggregate flow
      control for both modem and routers has been proposed in <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-credit-window" format="default"/>, and a control plane pause
      based mechanism is defined in <xref target="RFC8651" format="default"/>.
      The use of other flow control mechanisms simultaneously with
      Credit-Based Flow Control is not within the scope of this document.
      </t>
      <t>
      Credit-Based Flow Control, as a result of its proactive nature,
      may offer some advantages over a pause mechanism.
      Packet loss resulting from insufficient buffer space is less
      likely, as a transmitter does not send packets until the receiver
      has indicated that there is sufficient buffer available.
      </t>
      <t>
      <xref target="router-modem" format="default"/>  illustrates 
      a local node consisting of a router and a modem with a 
      DLEP.
      DLEP messages optionally contain a number of Data Items and 
      Sub-data Items.
      Traffic flow classification Data Items provided by the modem,
      are defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep-traffic-classification" format="default"/>.
      In this case, a flow is identified based on
      information found in a data plane header and one or more matches
      are associated with a single flow.
      Refer to Section 2.3 of <xref target="RFC2475" format="default"/>
      for general background on traffic classification.
      </t>
      <figure anchor="router-modem" align="left" suppress-title="false">
      <name slugifiedName="router_to_modem">Router and Modem DLEP Exchange</name>
      <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[                 
        
|--------------------Local Node--------------------|          
|                                                  |         
+-----------------------------+            +-------+          
| Router                      |            |Modem  |
|                             |            |Device |{~~~~~~~~} Remote 
|                             |            |       | Link      Nodes       
| Traffic Classification:     |            |       | Protocol    
| Per TID:                    |            |       | (e.g.,      
| DSCPs to FID / PCPs to FID  |            |       | 802.11)
|                             | Data Items |       | 
| Per Modem: (list of TIDs)   |<---------->|       | 
| FID to Credit Window Queues |============|       | 
|                             |            |       |      
+-----------------------------+            +-------+      
                              |            |
                              |----DLEP--- |
                              

]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
      This document defines DLEP Data Items which provide
      a flow control mechanism for traffic sent
      from a router to a modem. Flow control is provided using one or
      more logical "Credit Windows", each of which will typically be
      supported by an associated virtual or physical queue.
      Credit windows may be shared or dedicated on a per flow basis. The
      Data Items are structured to allow for reuse of the defined
      credit window based flow
      control with different traffic classification techniques.
      A router logically consumes credits for each credit window
      matching packet sent.
      </t>
      <t>
      Note that this document defines common Messages, Data Items and
      mechanisms that are reusable.  They are expected to be required by
      DLEP extensions defined in other documents such as found in <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep-da-credit-extension" format="default"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
      This document
      introduces support for  credit window control by defining two new DLEP
      messages in <xref target="sec-msgs" format="default"/>, and five new DLEP Data
      Items in <xref target="sec-data-items" format="default"/>.
      </t>
      <section anchor="sec-1.1" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Key Words</name>
        <t>
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
        BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119" format="default"/> <xref target="RFC8174" format="default"/> when, and
        only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="sec-cw-control" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Credit Window Control</name>
      <t>
    This section defines additions to DLEP used in credit based flow
    control.
    The use of credit window control impacts the data plane.
      </t>
      <t>
    The credit window control mechanisms defined in this document
    support credit based flow control of traffic sent from a router to a
    modem.  The mapping of specific flows to a particular
    credit window is based on the Traffic Classification Data Item
    defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep-traffic-classification" format="default"/>.
    Both types of DLEP peers, router and modem, negotiate the use of an
    extension employing this mechanism during session initialization as
    required, for example, by
    <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep-da-credit-extension" format="default"/>.
    When using
    credit windows, data traffic is only allowed to be sent by the
    router to the modem when there are credits available.
      </t>
      <t>
    Credits are managed on a per logical "Credit Window" basis.  Each
    credit window can be thought of as corresponding to a queue within a
    modem.  Credit windows may be shared across, or dedicated to,
    destinations and data plane identifiers, for example, DSCPs, at a
    granularity that is appropriate for a modem's implementation and its
    attached transmission technology.  As defined below in
    <xref target="sec-di-cwi" format="default"/>, there is a
    direct one-for-one mapping of credit windows to flows as identified
    by Flow Identifiers (FIDs) carried within the Traffic Classification Data Item.  Modems
    pass to the router information on their credit windows and FIDs
    prior to a router being able to send data when an extension
    requiring the use of credit window control is used.
    Note that TID and FID values are significant only to the issuing modem.
    There is no relationship implied by the same TID or FID value being
    issued by more than one modem.
    In addition to
    the traffic classification information associated with a FID,
    modems provide an initial credit window size, as well as the
    maximum size of the logical queue associated with each credit
    window.  The maximum size is included for informative and potential
    future uses.
      </t>
      <t>
    Modems provide an initial credit window size at the time of "Credit
    Window Initialization".  Such initialization can take place during
    session initiation or any point thereafter.  It can also take place
    when rate information changes.
    An increment to a Credit Window size, specified in a Credit Grant
    Data Item, is provided in a Destination Up or the new "Credit Control"
    Message.
    A router provides its view
    of the Credit Window, which is known as "Status", in Destination Up
    Response and the new "Credit Control Response" Messages.  Routers
    can also request credits using the new "Credit Control" Message.
      </t>
      <t>
    When modems provide credits to a router, they will need to take into
    account any overhead of their attached transmission technology and
    map it into the credit semantics defined in this document.  In
    particular, the credit window is defined below to include per frame
    (packet) MAC headers, and this may not match the actual overhead of
    the modem attached transmission technology.  In that case a direct
    mapping, or an approximation will need to be made by the modem to
    provide appropriate credit values.
      </t>
      <t>
    Actual flows of traffic are mapped to credit windows based on flow
    identification information provided by modems in the Traffic
    Classification Data Item defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep-traffic-classification" format="default"/>. This
    data item supports traffic classification on a per destination or
    more fine grain level.  Routers use the combination of the DLEP
    identified destination and flow information associated with a credit
    window in order to match traffic they send to specific credit
    windows.
    In some cases, the Traffic Classification Data Item allows
    the modem to specify a wildcard to match any packets that do not
    match other data items, for example see <xref target
    ="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep-ether-credit-extension"/>.
    In the absence of a wildcard, a packet may not match any of the data
    items and, in this case, SHOULD be dropped by the router.
      </t>
      <t>
    When a destination becomes reachable, a modem "associates"
    (identifies) the appropriate traffic classification information via
    the Traffic Class Identifier (TID) to be used for traffic sent by the router to that
    destination.
    This is supported by the Credit Window
    Association Data Item which is carried in Destination Up and Update
    messages, see <xref target="sec-di-cwa" format="default"/>.
    The TID provides the information to support router traffic
    classification, based on the FIDs contained in the TID, see <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep-traffic-classification" format="default"/>. 
    As defined,
    each credit window has a corresponding FID, so traffic is
    mapped to a credit window by locating a matching FID that is
    contained in the TID that is associated with the traffic's
    destination.
    This means that the use of FIDs, TIDs and the association of a
    TID to a DLEP destination enables a modem to share or dedicate
    resources as needed to match the specifics of its implementation and
    its attached transmission technology.
      </t>
      <t>
      The defined credit window control has similar objectives as the
      control found in <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-credit-window" format="default"/>.
      One notable difference from that credit control is that in this
      document, credits are never provided by the router to the modem.
      </t>

      <section anchor="data-plane" numbered="true">
        <name>Data Plane Considerations</name>
        <t>
      When credit windowing is used, a router MUST NOT send data traffic
      to a modem for forwarding if there is no matching classifier.
      If a matching classifier is found, a router MUST NOT send data
      traffic to a modem when there are no credits available in the
      associated Credit Window.
      <xref target="sec-cw-control" format="default"/> describes
      how classifiers are associated with destinations and how credit
      windows are associated with classifiers.
      Additionally, a router MUST ensure sufficient credits are available in the associated 
      Credit Window for the current data packet before sending that data packet to the modem. 
      The count of octets in the packet includes MAC overhead.
      In the example of Ethernet, framing, header and trailer are all
      included in this count.
      This document defines credit windows in octets and the credit
      window is decremented by the number of sent octets.
        </t>
        <t>
      A router MUST identify the credit window associated with traffic
      to be
      sent to a modem based on the traffic classification information
      provided in the Data Items defined in this document.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-msgs" numbered="true">
        <name>Credit Window Messages</name>
        <t>
      Two new messages are defined in support for credit window control:
      the Credit Control and the Credit Control Response Messages.  Sending
      and receiving both message types is REQUIRED to support the credit
      window control defined in this document.
        </t>
	
        <section anchor="sec-cc-msg" numbered="true">
          <name>Credit Control Message</name>
          <t>
        Credit Control Messages are sent by modems and routers. Each
        sender is only permitted to have one message outstanding at one
        time.  That is, a sender (either modem or router) MUST NOT send
        any subsequent Credit Control Message until a Credit
        Control Response Message is received from its peer.
          </t>
          <t>
        Credit Control Messages are sent by modems to provide credit
        window increases.  Modems send credit increases when there is
        transmission or local queue availability that exceeds the credit
        window value previously provided to the router. Modems will need to
        balance the load generated by sending and processing credit
        window increases against a router having data traffic available to send,
        but no credits available.
          </t>
          <t>
        Credit Control Messages MAY be sent by routers to request
        credits and provide window status. Routers will need to
        balance the load generated by sending and processing credit
        window requests against having data traffic available to send,
        but no credits available.
          </t>
          <t>
        The Message Type value in the DLEP Message Header is set to TBA2.
          </t>
          <t>
        A Credit Control message sent by a modem, MUST contain one or more
        Credit Window Grant Data Items as defined in <xref target="sec-di-grant" format="default"/>.  A router receiving this message MUST
        respond with a Credit Control Response Message.
          </t>
          <t>
        A Credit Control message sent by a router, MUST contain one or more Credit Window
        Request Data Items defined in <xref target="sec-di-request" format="default"/> and SHOULD contain a Credit Window
        Status Data Item, defined in <xref target="sec-di-status" format="default"/>,
        corresponding to each credit window request. A modem receiving
        this message MUST respond with a Credit Control Response
        Message based on the received message and Data Item and the
        processing defined in
        <xref target="sec-ccr-msg" format="default"/>,
        which will typically result in credit
        window increments being provided.
          </t>
          <t>
        Specific processing associated with each Credit Data Item is
        provided in
        <xref target="sec-data-items" format="default"/>.
          </t>
        </section>
	
        <section anchor="sec-ccr-msg" numbered="true">
          <name>Credit Control Response Message</name>
          <t>
        Credit Control Response Messages are sent by routers to report
        the current Credit Window for a destination.  A Credit Control
        Response message sent by
        a router, MUST contain one or more Credit Window Status Data
        Items as defined below in <xref target="sec-di-status" format="default"/>.
        Specific receive processing associated with the Credit Window
        Status Data Item is provided in <xref target="sec-di-status" format="default"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
        Credit Control Response Messages sent by modems MUST contain one
        or more Credit Window Grant Data Items. A Data Item for every
        Credit Window Request Data Item contained in the corresponding
        Credit Control Message received by the modem MUST be
        included.  Each Credit Grant Data Item MAY provide zero or more
        additional credits based on the modem's transmission or local
        queue availability.  Specific receive processing associated with
        each Grant Data Item is provided in <xref target="sec-di-grant" format="default"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
        The Message Type value in the DLEP Message Header is set to TBA3.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-data-items" numbered="true">
        <name>Credit Window Control Data Items</name>
        <t>
      Five new Data Items are defined to support credit window control.
      The Credit Window Initialization
      Data Item is used by a modem to identify a credit window and set its
      size.
      The Credit Window Association
      Data Item is used by a modem to identify which traffic classification
      identifiers (flows) should be used when sending traffic to a particular DLEP
      identified destination.
      The Credit Window Grant Data Item is used by a modem to provide additional
      credits to a router.
      The Credit Window Request Data Item is used by a router to request additional
      credits.
      The Credit Window Status Data Item is used to advertise the sender's view of
      number of available credits for state synchronization purposes.
        </t>
        <t>
      Any errors or inconsistencies encountered in parsing Data Items
      are handled in the same fashion as any other data item parsing error
      encountered in DLEP, see <xref target="RFC8175" format="default"/>. In particular, the
      node parsing the Data Item MUST terminate the session with a
      Status Data Item indicating Invalid Data.
        </t>
	
        <section anchor="sec-di-cwi" numbered="true">
          <name>Credit Window Initialization</name>
          <t>
        The Credit Window Initialization Data Item is used by a modem to
        identify a credit window and set its size.
        In order to avoid errors caused by the use of undefined FIDs or
        uninitialized credit windows, this Data Item SHOULD be included
        in any Session Initialization Response Message that indicates
        support for any such extension.
        Updates to
        previously identified credit windows or new credit windows MAY
        be sent by a modem by including the Data Item in Session Update
        Messages.  More than one data item MAY be included in a message
        to provide information on multiple credit windows.
          </t>
          <t>
        The Credit Window Initialization Data Item identifies a credit
        window using a Flow Identifier, or FID.  It also provides the
        size of the identified credit window.  To be used, a FID must be
        defined within a Traffic Classification Data Item and the
        associated TID must be provided via a Credit Window Association
        Data Item.
          </t>
          <t>
        The format of the Credit Window Initialization Data Item is:
          </t>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    | Data Item Type                | Length (16)                   |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    | Flow Identifier (FID)         |            Reserved           |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                         Credit Value                          |
    |                                                               |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |    Scale      |         Credit Window Max Size                |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
          <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
            <dt>Data Item Type:</dt>
            <dd>Data Item Type (TBA4)</dd>

            <dt>Length:</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>16</t>
              <t>
          As specified in <xref target="RFC8175"/>, Length is the number
          of octets in the Data Item.  It MUST be equal to sixteen
          (16). If it is some other value, the Data Item is corrupt so
          the message in which it appears cannot be reliably parsed and
          is ignored.
              </t>
            </dd>

            <dt>Flow Identifier (FID):</dt>
            <dd>
            A two-octet flow identifier as defined by the Traffic
            Classification Data Item <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep-traffic-classification" />.  The
            FID also uniquely identifies a credit window for a specific
            DLEP session.
            </dd>

            <dt>Reserved:</dt>
            <dd>
            MUST be set to zero by the sender (a modem) and validated by the
            receiver (a router).
	    A received non-zero value in Reserved is treated as an error.
          </dd>
            <dt>Credit Value:</dt>
            <dd>
            A 64-bit unsigned integer representing the credits, in octets, to
            be added to the Credit Window.  This value includes MAC
            headers as seen on the link between the modem and router.
          </dd>
            <dt>Scale:</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>
            An 8-bit unsigned integer indicating the scale used in the Credit Window
            Max Size field.  The valid values are:
              </t>
              <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
      Value  Scale
      ------------
          0   B - Bytes     (Octets)
          1  KB - Kilobytes (B/1024)
          2  MB - Megabytes (KB/1024)
          3  GB - Gigabytes (MB/1024)
              ]]></artwork>
            </dd>
            <dt>Credit Window Max Size:</dt>
            <dd>
            A 24-bit unsigned integer representing the maximum size, in the
            octet scale indicated by the Scale field, of the associated credit
            window.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>
        A router that receives a Credit Window Initialization Data Item
        MUST ensure that the FID field value has been provided by the
        modem in a Traffic Classification Data Item carried in either
        the current or a previous message.  If the FID cannot be found the
        router SHOULD log this information.
        The method of logging is left to the router implementation.
        Note that
        no traffic will be associated with the credit window in this
        case.  After FID validation, the router MUST locate the credit
        window that is associated with the FID indicated in each
        received Data Item.  If no associated credit window is found,
        the router MUST initialize a new credit window using the values
        carried in the Data Item.  When an associated credit window is
        found, the router MUST update the credit window and associated
        data plane state using the values carried in the Data Item.
        If the resulting Credit Value results in the credit window
        exceeding the represented Credit Window Max Size, the Credit
        Window Max Size field value is used as the new credit window size.
          </t>
          <t>
        It is worth noting, that such updates can result in a credit window
        size being reduced, for example, due to a transmission rate
        change on the modem.
        After sending the Session Update Message with one or more Credit
        Window Initialization Data Items that decrease the Credit Window
        Max Size, the modem SHOULD continue processing received packets
        that match the indicated FIDs, fit within the window for the
        unmodified Credit Window Max Size and arrive before the modem
        receives the corresponding Session Update Response Message.
        The modem SHOULD NOT issue additional credits for any affected
        FID until that FID's associated Window has drained to be
        less than the new Credit Window Max Size, regardless of when
        the corresponding Session Update Response Message is received.
          </t>
        </section>
	
        <section anchor="sec-di-cwa" numbered="true">
          <name>Credit Window Association</name>
          <t>
        The Credit Window Association Data Item is used by a modem to
        associate traffic classification information with a destination.
        The traffic classification information is identified using a TID
        value that has previously been sent by the modem or is listed
        in a Traffic Classification Data Item carried in the same message
        as the
        Credit Window Association
        Data Item.  TIDs in different Credit windows must not
        overlap.
          </t>
          <t>
        A single Credit Window Association Data Item MUST be included in every
        Destination Up and Destination Update Message sent by a modem when
        the credit window control defined in this document is used. Note
        that a TID will not be used unless it is listed in a Credit Window
        Association Data Item.
          </t>
          <t>
        The format of the Credit Window Association Data Item is:
          </t>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    | Data Item Type                | Length (2)                    |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |Traffic Class. Identifier (TID)|
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
          <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
            <dt>Data Item Type:</dt>
            <dd>Data Item Type (TBA5)</dd>

            <dt>Length:</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>2</t>
              <t>
          As specified in <xref target="RFC8175"/>, Length is the number
          of octets in the Data Item. It MUST be equal to two (2). If it
          is some other value, the Data Item is corrupt so the message
          in which it appears cannot be reliably parsed and is ignored.
              </t>
            </dd>
            <dt> Traffic Classification Identifier (TID):</dt>
            <dd>
            A 16-bit unsigned integer identifying a traffic
            classification set that has been identified in a Traffic
            Classification Data Item, see <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep-traffic-classification" format="default"/>.
          </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>
        A router that receives a Credit Window Association Data Item MUST
        locate the traffic classification information indicated by the
        received TID.  If no corresponding information is found, the
        Credit Window Association
        Data Item MUST be treated as an error as described above.
        If the traffic classification information is located, the
        router MUST ensure that any data plane state that is associated
        with the TID and its corresponding FIDs are updated as needed
        (per <xref target="data-plane" format="default"/>).
        If a
        router determines that a newly received Data Item results in
        credit windows with overlapping TIDs, the Data Item MUST be
        treated as an error as described above.
          </t>
        </section>
	
        <section anchor="sec-di-grant" numbered="true">
          <name>Credit Window Grant</name>
          <t>
        The Credit Window Grant Data Item is used by a modem to
        provide credits to a router.  One or more Credit Window Grant Data
        Items MAY be carried in the DLEP Destination Up, Destination Announce
        Response, Destination Update, Credit Control Messages, and Credit
        Control Response Messages.
        Multiple Credit Window Grant Data Items may be present in a
        single message.
        Each item grants credits to a different credit window and,
        therefor, references a different FID.
        In all
        message types, this Data Item provides an additional number of octets
        to be added to the indicated credit window.  Credit windows are
        identified using FID values that have been previously been
        sent by the modem or are listed in a Credit Window Initialization
        Data Item carried in the same message as the Data Item.
          </t>
          <t>
        The format of the Credit Window Grant Data Item is:
          </t>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | Data Item Type                | Length (12)                   |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | Flow Identifier (FID)         |            Reserved           |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                     Additional Credits                        |
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
          <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
            <dt>Data Item Type:</dt>
            <dd>Data Item Type (TBA6)</dd>

            <dt>Length:</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>12</t>
              <t>
          As specified in <xref target="RFC8175"/>, Length is the number
          of octets in the Data Item.  It MUST be equal to twelve
          (12). If it is some other value, the Data Item is corrupt so
          the message in which it appears cannot be reliably parsed and
          is ignored.
              </t>
            </dd>
            <dt>Flow Identifier (FID):</dt>
            <dd>
            A two-octet flow identifier as defined by the Traffic
            Classification Data Item.  The FID also uniquely indicates a
            credit window.
            </dd>

            <dt>Reserved:</dt>
            <dd>
            MUST be set to zero by the sender and verified by the
            receiver.
	    A received non-zero value in Reserved is treated as an error.
          </dd>
            <dt>Additional Credit:</dt>
            <dd>
            A 64-bit unsigned integer representing the credits, in octets, to
            be added to the Credit Window.  This value includes MAC
            headers as seen on the link between the modem and router. A value
          of zero indicates that no additional credits are being provided.</dd>
          </dl>
          <t>
        When receiving this Data Item, a router MUST identify the credit
        window indicated by the FID.  If the FID is not known to the router,
        it SHOULD log this information and discard the Data Item.
        The method of logging is left to the router implementation.
        It is important to note that while this Data Item can be received in a
        destination specific message, credit windows are managed independently
        from the destination identified in the message carrying this Data
        Item, and the indicated FID MAY even be disjoint from the identified
        destination.
          </t>
          <t>
        Once the credit window is identified, the credit window size MUST be
        increased by the value contained in the Additional Credits field.  If
        the increase results in a window overflow, the Credit Window
        must be set to its maximum as defined by the Credit Window Max
        Size carried in the Credit Window Initialization Data Item.
          </t>
          <t>
        No response is sent by the router to a modem after processing a Credit
        Window Grant Data Item received in a Credit Control Response Message.
        When a Credit Window Grant Data Item is received in other message types,
        the receiving router MUST send a
        Credit Window Status Data Item or items reflecting the
        resulting Credit Window value of the updated credit window.  When the
        Credit Grant Data Item is received in a Destination Up Message, the
        Credit Window Status Data Item(s) MUST be sent in the
        corresponding Destination Up Response Message.  Otherwise, a
        Credit Control Message MUST be sent.
          </t>
        </section>
	
        <section anchor="sec-di-status" numbered="true">
          <name>Credit Window Status</name>
          <t>
        The Credit Window Status Data Item is used by
        a router to report the current credit window size to its peer modem.  One
        or more Credit Window Status Data Items MAY be carried in a
        Destination Up Response Message or a Credit Control Response Message.
        As discussed in
        <xref target="sec-di-grant" format="default"/>,
        the Destination Up Response Message is used when
        the Data Item is sent in response to a Destination Up Message, and
        the Credit Control Response Message is sent in response to a Credit
        Control Message.  Multiple Credit Window Status Data Items in a
        single message are used to indicate different sizes of different
        credit windows.  Similar to the Credit Window Grant, credit windows
        are identified using FID values that have been previously been sent
        by the modem.
          </t>
          <t>
        The format of the Credit Window Status Data Item is:
          </t>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | Data Item Type                | Length (12)                   |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | Flow Identifier (FID)         |            Reserved           |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                  Current Credit Window Size                   |
   |                                                               |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
          <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
            <dt>Data Item Type:</dt>
            <dd>Data Item Type (TBA7)</dd>

            <dt>Length:</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>12</t>
              <t>
          As specified in <xref target="RFC8175"/>, Length is the number
          of octets in the Data Item. It MUST be equal to twelve
          (12). If it is some other value, the Data Item is corrupt so
          the message in which it appears cannot be reliably parsed and
          is ignored.
              </t>
            </dd>

            <dt>Flow Identifier (FID):</dt>
            <dd>
            A two-octet flow identifier as defined by the Traffic
            Classification Data Item.  The FID also uniquely identifies
            a credit window.
            </dd>

            <dt>Reserved:</dt>
            <dd>
            MUST be set to zero by the sender and verified by the
            receiver.
	    A received non-zero value in Reserved is treated as an error.
          </dd>
            <dt>Current Credit Window Size:</dt>
            <dd>
            A 64-bit unsigned integer, indicating
            the current number of credits, in octets, available for the
                    router to send to the modem. 
                    This is referred to as the Modem Receive Window in
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-credit-window" format="default"/>.
          </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>
        When receiving this Data Item, a modem MUST identify the credit
        window indicated by the FID.  If the FID is not known to the modem,
        it SHOULD log this information and discard the Data Item.
        The method of logging is left to the modem implementation.
        As with the Credit Window Grant Data Item, the FID MAY be unrelated to
        the Destination indicated in the message carrying the Data Item.
          </t>
          <t>
        Once the credit window is identified, the modem SHOULD check the
        received Current Credit Window Size field value against the outstanding credit
        window's available credits at the time the most recent Credit Window
        Initialization or Grant Data Item associated with the indicated FID
        was sent.  If the difference in values is greater than can
        be accounted for based on observed data frames, then the modem SHOULD
        send a Credit Window Initialization Data Item to reset the associated
        credit window size to the modem's current view of the available
        credits.  As defined in
        <xref target="sec-di-cwi" format="default"/>,
        Credit Window Initialization Data Items are
        sent in Session Update Messages.  When multiple Data Items need to be
        sent, they SHOULD be combined into a single message when possible.
        Alternatively, and also in cases where there are small differences,
        the modem MAY adjust the values sent in Credit Window Grant Data Items
        to account for the reported Credit Window.
          </t>
        </section>
	
        <section anchor="sec-di-request" numbered="true">
          <name>Credit Window Request</name>
          <t>
        The Credit Window Request Data Item is used by a router to
        request additional credits for particular credit windows.  Credit
        Window Request Data Items are carried in Credit Control Messages, and
        one or more Credit Window Request Data Items MAY be present in a
        message.
          </t>
          <t>
        Credit windows are identified using a FID as defined in <xref target="sec-di-cwi" format="default"/>.  Multiple FIDs MAY be present to allow for the
        case where the router identifies that credits are needed in multiple
        credit windows.  A special FID value, as defined below, is used to
        indicate that a credit request is being made across all queues.
          </t>
          <t>
        The format of the Credit Window Request Data Item is:
          </t>
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | Data Item Type                | Length                        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | Flow Identifier (FID) [1]     | Flow Identifier (FID) [2]     |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |               ...             | Flow Identifier (FID) [n]     |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
          <dl newline="true" spacing="normal">
            <dt>Data Item Type:</dt>
            <dd>Data Item Type (TBA8)</dd>

            <dt>Length:</dt>
            <dd>
              <t>Variable</t>
              <t>
          As specified in <xref target="RFC8175"/>, Length is the number
          of octets in the Data Item, excluding the Type and Length
          fields.  It is equal to the number of FID fields carried in
          the Data Item times 2 and MUST be at least 2. If it is less
          than 2, the Data Item is corrupt so the message in which it
          appears cannot be reliably parsed and is ignored.
              </t>
            </dd>
            <dt>Flow Identifier (FID):</dt>
            <dd>
            A two-octet flow identifier as defined by the Traffic
            Classification Data Item.  The FID also uniquely identifies
            a credit window.  The special value of 0xFFFF indicates that
            the request applies to all FIDs.  When this special value is
            included, all other FID values included in the Data Item are
            redundant as the special value indicates all FIDs.
          </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>
        A modem receiving this Data Item MUST provide a Credit Increment for
        the indicated credit windows via Credit Window Grant Data Items
        carried in a new Credit Control Message.  Multiple values and queue
        indexes SHOULD be combined into a single Credit Control Message when
        possible.  Unknown FID values SHOULD be logged and then
        ignored by the modem.
        The method of logging is left to the modem implementation.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section anchor="sec-mgmnt" numbered="true">
        <name>Management Considerations</name>
        <t>
      This section provides several network management guidelines
      to implementations supporting the credit window mechanisms defined
      in this document.
        </t>
        <t>
      Modems MAY support the configuration of the number of credit
      windows (queues) to advertise to a router.
        </t>
        <t>
      Routers may have limits on the number of queues that they can
      support.  They may even have limits on supported credit window
      combinations.  For example, per destination queues may not be
      supported at all.  When modem-provided credit window information
      exceeds the capabilities of a router, the router SHOULD use a subset of
      the provided credit windows.  Alternatively, a router MAY reset the
      session and indicate that the extension is not supported.  In either
      case, the mismatch of capabilities SHOULD be reported to the user via
      normal network management mechanisms, such as the user interface
      or error logging.
        </t>
        <t>
      In all cases, if credit windows are in use, traffic for which credits are not
      available MUST NOT be sent to the modem by the router.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-compat" numbered="true">
      <name>Compatibility</name>
      <t>
    The messages and Data Items defined in this document will only be used when
    extensions require their use.
      </t>
      <t>
    The DLEP specification <xref target="RFC8175" format="default"/> defines handling of unexpected
    appearances of any Data Items, including those defined in this
    document.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-sec" numbered="true">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
    This document introduces credit window control and flow mechanisms
    to DLEP.  These mechanisms expose vulnerabilities similar to existing
    DLEP messages.
    For example, a malicious actor masquerading as a DLEP peer could
    inject a Credit Window Initialization Data Item which resizes a
    credit window to a value that results in a denial of service.
    The transport layer security mechanisms documented in
    <xref target="RFC8175" format="default"/> can, with some updates,
    be applied to this document.
    Implementations following the "networked deployment" model described
    in the "Implementation Scenarios" of
    <xref target="RFC8175" format="default"/> SHOULD refer to
    <xref target="BCP195" format="default"/> for additional details.
    The Layer 2 security mechanisms documented in
    <xref target="RFC8175" format="default"/> can also, with some updates,
    be applied to the mechanism defined in this document.
    Examples of technologies that can be deployed to secure the Layer
    2 link include <xref target="IEEE-802.1AE"/> and <xref target="IEEE-8802-1X"/>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="sec-iana" numbered="true">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>
    This document requests the assignment of several values by IANA.  All
    assignments are to registries defined by <xref target="RFC8175" format="default"/>.
      </t>

      <section anchor="sec-iana-msg" numbered="true">
        <name>Message Type Values</name>
        <t>
      This document requests 2 new assignments to the DLEP Message Registry
      named "Message Values" in the range with the "Specification Required"
      policy.  The requested values are as follows:
        </t>
        <t keepWithNext="true"/>
        <table anchor="table_msg" align="center">
          <name>Requested Message Type Values</name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">Type Code</th>
              <th align="left">Description</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">TBA2</td>
              <td align="left">Credit Control</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">TBA3</td>
              <td align="left">Credit Control Response</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t keepWithPrevious="true"/>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sec-iana-di" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Data Item Values</name>
        <t>
      This document requests the following new assignments to the DLEP Data Item
      Registry named "Data Item Type Values" in the range with the "Specification
      Required" policy.  The requested values are as follows:
        </t>
        <t keepWithNext="true"/>
        <table anchor="table_di" align="center">
          <name>Requested Data Item Values</name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left">Type Code</th>
              <th align="left">Description</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">TBA4</td>
              <td align="left">Credit Window Initialization</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">TBA5</td>
              <td align="left">Credit Window Association</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">TBA6</td>
              <td align="left">Credit Window Grant</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">TBA7</td>
              <td align="left">Credit Window Status</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td align="left">TBA8</td>
              <td align="left">Credit Window Request</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <t keepWithPrevious="true"/>
      </section>
    </section>
</middle>

<back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8175.xml"/>
        <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep-traffic-classification"
                   target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-manet-dlep-traffic-classification">
          <front>
	    <title>Dynamic Link Exchange Protocol (DLEP) Traffic
	    Classification Data Item</title>
	    <author fullname="Bow-Nan Cheng" initials="B."
	  	    surname="Cheng">
	      <organization>MIT Lincoln Laboratory</organization>
	    </author>
	    <author fullname="David Wiggins" initials="D."
		    surname="Wiggins"/>
	    <author fullname="Lou Berger" initials="L." surname="Berger">
	      <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
	    </author>
	    <author fullname="Don Fedyk" initials="D." surname="Fedyk">
	       <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
	    </author>
	    <date day="19" month="November" year="2024"/>
	  </front>
	  <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
		      value="draft-ietf-manet-dlep-traffic-classification"/>
        </reference>
      </references>

      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
	<reference anchor="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep-da-credit-extension"
		   target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-manet-dlep-da-credit-extension/">
	  <front>
	    <title>DLEP DiffServ Aware Credit Window Extension</title>
	    <author fullname="Bow-Nan Cheng" initials="B."
		    surname="Cheng">
	      <organization>MIT Lincoln Laboratory</organization>
	    </author>
	    <author fullname="David Wiggins" initials="D."
		    surname="Wiggins"/>
	    <author fullname="Lou Berger" initials="L."
		    surname="Berger">
	      <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
	    </author>
	    <author fullname="Donald E. Eastlake 3rd" initials="D. E."
		    surname="Eastlake">
	      <organization>Independent</organization>
	    </author>
	    <date day="15" month="December" year="2024"/>
	  </front>
	  <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
	    value="draft-ietf-manet-dlep-da-credit-extension"/>
	</reference>
	<reference anchor="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep-ether-credit-extension"
		   target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-manet-dlep-ether-credit-extension/">
	  <front>
	    <title>DLEP IEEE 802.1Q Aware Credit Window
	    Extension</title>
	    <author fullname="David Wiggins" initials="D."
		    surname="Wiggins"/>
	    <author fullname="Lou Berger" initials="L."
		    surname="Berger">
	      <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>

	    </author>
	    <author fullname="Donald E. Eastlake 3rd" initials="D. E."
		    surname="Eastlake">
	      <organization>Independent</organization>
	    </author>
	    <date day="15" month="December" year="2024"/>
	  </front>
	  <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
		      value="draft-ietf-manet-dlep-ether-credit-extension"/>
	</reference>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-manet-credit-window.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2475.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8651.xml"/>
	<referencegroup anchor="BCP195" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/bcp195">
          <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9325.xml"/>
          <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8996.xml"/>
        </referencegroup>
	<reference anchor="IEEE-802.1AE" target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8585421">
	  <front>
	      <title>IEEE Standard for Local and metropolitan area networks-Media Access Control (MAC) Security Amendment 4: MAC Privacy protection</title>
	      <author/>
          </front>
        </reference>
	<reference anchor="IEEE-8802-1X" target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/9650828">
	  <front>
	      <title>8802-1X-2021 - IEEE/ISO/IEC International Standard-Telecommunications and exchange between information technology systems--Requirements for local and metropolitan area networks--Part 1X:Port-based network access control</title>
	      <author/>
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>

    <section numbered="true">
      <name>Acknowledgments</name>
      <t>
     We mourn the loss of Stan Ratliff who passed away on October 22,
     2019. His guidance, leadership and personal contributions were
     critical in the development of this work and DLEP as a whole. His
     leadership and friendship shall be missed.
      </t>
      <t>
     We had the honor of working too briefly with David Wiggins on this
     and related DLEP work. His contribution to the IETF and publication
     of the first and definitive open source DLEP implementation have
     been critical to the acceptance of DLEP. We morn his passing on
     November 23, 2023.  We wish to recognize his guidance, leadership
     and professional excellence.  We were fortunate to benefit from his
     leadership and friendship. He shall be missed.
      </t>
      <t>
     Many useful comments were
     received from contributors to the MANET working group, notably Rick
     Taylor, Ronald in't Velt, David Black and Donald E. Eastlake.
     This
     document was derived from <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep-da-credit-extension" format="default"/> as a result of
     discussions at IETF 101.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section  anchor="Tree" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Example DLEP Credit Flow Control and Traffic Classification Data Item Exchange</name>
      <t>
        Below <xref target="dlep-exchange" format="default"/> illustrates
        a credit flow control and traffic classification exchange between
        a Router and a Modem.
        The Modem will initialize a number of queues with Credit Window
        Initialization Data Items, Window Association Data Item(s)
        and Traffic Classification Item(s) included in DLEP messages as
        outlined in this document.
        If the Data Items are successfully validated, traffic is mapped
        to the corresponding credit window on the router and forwarded
        when there are sufficient credits.
        Routers can periodically report the status of the credit window.
        Modems will send periodic updates with more credits as packets are
        transmitted.  Routers may request more credits for a particular
        window if the router requires more credits.

        This document defines window credit flow information for flow
        Identifiers (FIDs) that map to the queues.
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep-traffic-classification" format="default"/>
        defines the traffic classification data sub items such as DiffServ
        code points that map to the FIDs.
      </t>
       <figure anchor="dlep-exchange" align="left" suppress-title="false">
         <name slugifiedName="dlep_exchange">Example DLEP Traffic Classification/Credit Flow Exchange</name>
         <artwork name="" type="" align="center" alt=""><![CDATA[
Router                                        Modem

  |<----------------DLEP Messages---------------|
  |   Traffic Classification Data Item(s)       |
  |   Window Association Data Item(s)           |
  |   Credit Window Initialization Data Item(s) |
  |                                             |
  |============================================>|
  |   Traffic                                   |
  |                                             |
  |<----------------DLEP Messages---------------|
  |   Credit Window Grant Data Item(s)          | T
  |============================================>| i
  |   Traffic                                   | m
  |                                             | e
  |----------------DLEP Messages--------------->|
  |   Credit Window Status Data Item(s)         | |
  |                                             | V
  |============================================>|
  |   Traffic                                   |
  |                                             |
  |----------------DLEP Messages--------------->|
  |   Credit Window Request Data Item(s)        |
  |                                             |
  |<------------------------------------------- |
  |   Credit Window Grant Data Item(s)          |
  |                                             |
  |============================================>|
  |   Traffic                                   |
  |                                             |
]]></artwork>
       </figure>
    </section>

</back>

</rfc>
