<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  ]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<rfc category="std" ipr="trust200902"
     docName="draft-ietf-manet-dlep-da-credit-extension-01">

<front>
<title abbrev="DLEP DA Credit Extension">DLEP DiffServ Aware Credit Windowing 
Extension</title> 
   <author initials='B.' surname="Cheng" fullname='Bow-Nan Cheng'>
    <organization>Lincoln Laboratory</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</street>
        <street>244 Wood Street</street>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <region>MA</region>
        <code>02420-9108</code>
      </postal>
       <email>bcheng@ll.mit.edu</email>
    </address>
    </author>
   <author initials='D.' surname="Wiggins" fullname='David Wiggins'>
    <organization>Lincoln Laboratory</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</street>
        <street>244 Wood Street</street>
        <city>Lexington</city>
        <region>MA</region>
        <code>02420-9108</code>
      </postal>
       <email>David.Wiggins@ll.mit.edu</email>
    </address>
    </author>
   <author initials='L.' surname="Berger" fullname='Lou Berger'>
    <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
    <address>
       <email>lberger@labn.net</email>
    </address>
    </author>

  <date/>
  <abstract>
<t>
  This document defines an extension to the DLEP protocol that enables a
  DiffServ aware credit-windowing scheme for destination-specific flow
  control.
</t>
</abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section anchor="sec-1" title="Introduction">
<t>
  The Dynamic Link Event Protocol (DLEP) is defined in <xref
  target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep"/>. It provides the exchange of link
  related control information between DLEP peers.  DLEP peers are 
  comprised of a modem and a router. DLEP defines a base set of
  mechanisms as well as support for possible extensions.  This
  document defines one such extension.
</t>
<t>
  The base DLEP specification does not include any flow control
  capability.  There are various flow control theoretically possible
  with DLEP.  For example, a credit-windowing scheme for
  destination-specific flow control which provides aggregate flow
  control for both modem and routers has been proposed in <xref
  target="I-D.ietf-manet-credit-window"/>.
</t>
<t>
  This document defines a DLEP extension which provides flow control for
  DiffServ <xref target="RFC2475"/> traffic sent from a router to a
  modem. Flow control is provided for multiple DSCPs (differentiated
  services codepoint), which are grouped into logical sets of logical
  queues. The extension defined in this document is referred to as
  "DiffServ Aware Credit Windowing" or, more simply, the "DA Credit"
  extension.
</t>
<t>
  This document defines a new DLEP Extension Type Value in <xref
  target="sec-ext-type"/> which is used to indicate the use of the
  extension. Two new messages are defined in <xref
  target="sec-msgs"/>, and four new DLEP Data Items in <xref
  target="sec-data-items"/>.
</t>
<section anchor="sec-1.1" title="Key Words">
<t>
   The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
   "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
   "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
   14, RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
</t>
</section>
</section>
<section anchor="sec-theory" title="Extension Overview">
  <t>
    The DA Credit extension can be used to support credit based flow
    control of traffic sent from a router to a modem.  The extension can
    be used to support DiffServ and non-DiffServ based flow control.
    Both types of DLEP endpoints, i.e., a router and a modem, negotiate
    the use of extension during session initialization, see Section 5.2
    <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep"/>.
  </t>
  <t>
    When the extension is to be used, a modem passes to a router its
    known DSCPs, if any. DSCPs are grouped by logical queues, each of
    which are given a logical queue index.  The queue index zero (0) is
    special and is used for any DSCP value, including 0, which is not
    otherwise identified by the modem.  The modem also provides a size,
    in bytes, of the logical queue for informative and, potential,
    future uses. Currently, only DSCP to logical queue index value
    mapping is used in flow control operation.
  </t>
  <t>
    The DA Credit extension supports credit based flow control on a per
    MAC address destination, per queue index basis.  Modems provide the
    initial size of the associated "Credit Window", i.e., the amount in
    octets (bytes) that may be sent by the router to the modem, when a
    MAC destination becomes reachable and, optionally, when its rate
    information changes. "Credit Increments", i.e., increases in a
    Credit Window size, are provided using new "Credit Control"
    messages.  A router provides its view of the Credit Window, which is
    known as "status", in Destination Up Response and the new "Credit
    Control Response" messages.  Routers can also request credits using
    the new "Credit Control" message.
  </t>
  <t>
    Credit information, both grants and status, is provided in new
    credit grant related data items.  Each data item contains a single
    credit value that applies to one or more queue indexes.  Different
    (grant and status) values for different queue indexes can be
    provided in a single message by including multiple grant data items.
    The values indicate a number of octets (bytes), including MAC
    headers on the router to modem link, that may be sent.
  </t>
  <t>
    Note that credit information related to different destination MAC
    addresses is always passed in different DLEP messages.
  </t>
<t>
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="sec-ext-type" title="Extension Usage and Identification">
<t>
   The use of the extension defined in this document SHOULD be
   configurable.  To indicate that the DiffServ Aware Credit Windowing
   Extension is to be used, an implementation MUST include the DiffServ
   Aware Credit Windowing Type Value in the Extensions Supported Data
   Item. The Extensions Supported Data Item is sent and processed
   according to <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep"/>.
</t>
<t>
  The DiffServ Aware Credit Windowing Extension Type Value is TBA1, see
  <xref target="sec-iana"/>.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="sec-msgs" title="Extension Messages">
  <t>
    Two new messages are defined by this extension: the Credit Control
    and the Credit Control Response message.  Sending and receiving both
    message types MUST be supported by any implementation that
    advertises use of this extension per <xref target="sec-ext-type"/>.
  </t>
  <section anchor="sec-cc-msg" title="Credit Control Message">
    <t>
      Credit Control Messages are sent by modems to provide Credit
      Increments. For messages sent by modems, only one message per MAC
      address can be outstanding at one time.  That is, a modem MUST
      NOT send a second (or any subsequent) message containing the same
      MAC Address until a Credit Control Response message is received
      from its peer router with that MAC address.
    </t>
    <t>
      Credit Control Messages MAY be sent by routers, e.g., to request
      credits or provide window status.  No specific response message is
      required from a message transaction perspective.
    </t>
    <t>
      [TBD: Should anything be said about sending, or limiting, multiple
      credit requests?]
    </t>
    <t>
      The Message Type value in the DLEP Message Header is set to TBA2.
    </t>
    <t>
      The message MUST contain a DLEP MAC Address Data Item.
    </t>
    <t>
      A message sent by a modem, MUST contain one or more DiffServ Aware
      Credit Grant data items as defined below in <xref
      target="sec-di-grant"/>.  A router receiving this message MUST
      respond with a Credit Control Response Message.
    </t>
    <t>
      A message sent by a router, MUST contain the DiffServ Aware Credit
      Request data item defined below in <xref
      target="sec-di-request"/>.  A modem receiving this message MUST
      provide a Credit Increment for the indicated MAC address and queue
      indexes via a new Credit Control Message.
    </t>
    <t>
      Specific processing associated with each Credit data item is
      provided below.
    </t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="sec-ccr-msg" title="Credit Control Response Message">
    <t>
      Credit Control Response Messages are sent by
      routers to report the current Credit Window for a destination.
    </t>
    <t>
      The Message Type value in the DLEP Message Header is set to TBA3.
    </t>
    <t>
      The message MUST contain a DLEP MAC Address Data Item.
    </t>
    <t>
      A message sent by a router, MUST contain one or more DiffServ
      Aware Credit Window Status data items as defined below in <xref
      target="sec-di-status"/>.
    </t>
    <t>
      Specific processing associated with the DA Credit Window Status
      data item is provided below.
    </t>
    <t>
    </t>
  </section>
</section>
<section anchor="sec-data-items" title="Extension Data Items">
<t>
   Four data items are defined by this extension. The Queue Parameters
   Data Item is used by a modem to provide information on the DSCPs it
   uses in forwarding.
   The DA Credit Grant is used by a modem to provide credits
   to a router.
   The DA Credit Request is used by a router to request additional
   credits. 
   The DA Credit Window Status is used to advertise the sender's view of
   number of available credits for synchronization purposes.  
</t>
<t>
  The defined data items and operations are similar to those found in
  <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-credit-window"/>.  One notable difference
  from this extension is that in this document credits are never
  provided by the router to the modem.
</t>
<section anchor="sec-di-qp" title="Queue Parameters">
<t>
  The Queue Parameters Data Item is used by a modem to indicate DSCP
  values that may be independently controlled.  This data item MUST be
  included in a Session Initialization Response Message that also
  contains the DiffServ Aware Credit Windowing Extension Type Value in
  the Extensions Supported Data Item.  Updates to these parameters MAY
  be sent by a modem by including the data item in Session Update
  Messages.
</t>
<t>
  The Queue Parameters Data Item identifies DSCPs based on groups of
  logical queues. The number of logical queues is variable as is the
  number of DSCPs associated with each queue. A queue size (in bytes)
  is provided for informational purposes.  An implementation that does
  not support DSCPs would indicate 1 queue with 0 DSCPs, and the number
  of bytes that may be in its associated link transmit queue.
</t>
<t>
  The format of the Queue Parameters Data Item is:
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
     0                   1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    | Data Item Type                | Length                        |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |   Num Queues  | Scale |              Reserved                 |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |Num DSCPs Q0(0)|             Queue Size Q0                     |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    | Num DSCPs Q1  |             Queue Size Q1                     |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    | Num DSCPs Q2  |             Queue Size Q2                     |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    :                                ...                            :
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    | Num DSCPs Qn  |             Queue Size Qn                     |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |  DS Field Q1  |  DS Field Q1  |  DS Field Q1  |  DS Field Q2  |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    :                                ...            |  DS Field Qn  |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
  <list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Data Item Type:">TBA4</t>
    <t hangText="Length:">Variable
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      Per <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep"/> Length
      is the number of octets in the data item, excluding the Type and
      Length fields.
    </t>
    <t hangText="Num Queues:">
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      An 8-bit unsigned integer indicating the number of queues
      represented in the data item.  This field MUST contain a value of
      at least one (1). Note that this number is one
      larger than the largest queue index value included in the data
      item.
    </t>
    <t hangText="Scale:">
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      An 4-bit unsigned integer indicating the scale used in the Queue
      Size fields. The valid values are:
      <figure>
        <artwork>
      Value  Scale
      ------------
          0   B - Bytes     (Octets)
          1  KB - Kilobytes (B/1024)
          2  MB - Megabytes (KB/1024)
          3  GB - Gigabytes (MB/1024)
        </artwork>
      </figure>
    </t>
    <t hangText="Reserved:">
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      MUST be set to zero by the sender (a modem) and ignored by the
      receiver (a router).
    </t>
    <t hangText="Num DSCPs Qn:">
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      An 8-bit unsigned integer indicating the number of DSCPs
      associated with the indexed queue.  Other than the special case
      covered in the next paragraph, this field MUST contain a value of
      at least one (1).  Queue indexes start at zero (0) and the maximum
      queue index "Qn" is one less than the value carried in the Num
      Queues field. Queue indexes are implicit in the position in the
      data item.

      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      Queue index zero "Q0" is a special case. It is used for any
      traffic that does not carry a DSCP value represented in the data
      item.  Therefore the value of the Queue index zero field, "Num
      DSCPs Q0", field MUST be zero (0).
    </t>
    <t hangText="Queue Size Qn:">
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      A 24-bit unsigned integer representing the size, in the octet
      scale indicated by the Scale field, of the queue supporting
      traffic with the DSCPs associated with the queue index.
    </t>
    <t hangText="DS Field Qn:">
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      The data item contains a sequence of 8 bit DS Fields.  The
      position in the sequence identifies the associated queue
      index. The number of DS Fields present should equal the sum of all
      Num DSCPs field values.  
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      The DS Field structure is the same as <xref target="RFC2474"/>.
      <figure>
        <artwork>
        0   1   2   3   4   5   6   7
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+
      |         DSCP          |  CU   |
      +---+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+

        DSCP: differentiated services codepoint
        CU:   currently unused, MUST be zero
        </artwork>
      </figure>
    </t>
  </list>
    </t>
</section>
<section anchor="sec-di-grant" title="DiffServ Aware (DA) Credit Grant">
<t>
   The DiffServ Aware, or DA, Credit Grant data item is used by a modem
   to provide credits to a router. One or more DA Credit Grant data
   items MAY be carried in the DLEP Destination Up, Destination Announce
   Response, Destination Update, and Credit Control messages.  Multiple
   DA Credit Grant data items in a single message are used to indicated
   different credit values for different logical queues.
</t>
<t>
   In Destination type messages, this data item provides the total
   number of octets available in the Credit Window to the destination
   indicated in the message for the specified logical queues.  In the
   Credit Control message, this data item provides an additional number
   of octets to be added to the Credit Window to the destination
   indicated in the message for the specified logical queues.
</t>
<t>
   Logical queues are identified using a Queue Index as defined above in
   <xref target="sec-di-qp"/>.  Multiple Queue Indexes MAY be present to
   allow for the case where same credit information applies to multiple
   queues. As mentioned above, multiple DA Credit Grant Data Items MAY
   be present to provide different queue-specific credit information in
   one message. The special Queue Index value of 255 is used to indicate
   that the credit information applies to all queues.
</t>
<t>
  The format of the DA Credit Grant Data Item is:
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | Data Item Type                | Length                        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                         Credit Value                          |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                         Credit value                          |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |  Queue Index  |               ...                             :
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   :                                ...            |  Queue Index  |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
  <list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Data Item Type:">TBA5</t>
    <t hangText="Length:">Variable
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      Per <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep"/>, Length
      is the number of octets in the data item, excluding the Type and
      Length fields. It will equal 8 plus the number of Queue Index
      fields carried in the data item and MUST be at least 9.
    </t>
    <t hangText="Credit Value:">
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      A 64-bit unsigned integer representing the credits, in octets, to
      be applied to the Credit Window.  This value includes MAC
      headers as seen on the link between the modem and router.</t>
    <t hangText="Queue Index:">
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      One or more 8-bit fields used to indicate a queue index defined by
      a Queue Parameters Data Item.  The special value of 255 indicates
      that the information in the data item applies to all queue indexes.
    </t>
  </list>
</t>

<t>
  Receive processing of this data item is based on the message in which
  it is carried.  When this data item is received in a Destination type
  message, the Credit Window of the indicated destination MAC address
  and indicated queue indexes MUST be set to the value contained in the
  Credit Value field.  
</t>
<t>
  When this data item is received in a Credit Control message, the
  Credit Window of the indicated destination MAC address and indicated
  queue indexes MUST be increased by the value contained in the Credit
  Value field. If the increase results in a window overflow, i.e., the
  Credit Window resulting after the increase is smaller than the
  original Credit Window, the Credit Window must be set to its maximum
  (0xFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFF).
</t>
<t>
  Independent of the received message, the receiving router MUST send a
  DA Credit Window Status data item or items reflecting the resulting
  Credit Window value of each modified queue index.  When the Credit
  Grant data item is received in a Destination Up message, the DA Credit
  Window Status data item(s) MUST be sent in the corresponding
  Destination Up Response message. In all other cases, the a Credit
  Control message MUST be sent.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="sec-di-status" title="DiffServ Aware (DA) Credit Window Status">
<t>
   The DiffServ Aware, or DA, Credit Window Status data item is used by
   a router to report the current Credit Window to its peer modem.  One
   or more DA Credit Window Status data items MAY be carried in a
   Destination Up Response message or a Credit Control Response message.
   As discussed above, the Destination Up Response message is used when
   the data item is sent in response to a Destination Up message, and
   the Credit Control Response message is sent in response to a Credit
   Control message.  Multiple DA Credit Window Status data items in a
   single message are used to indicated different credit window values
   for different logical queues.
</t>
<t>
   Similar to the DA Credit Grant, logical queues are identified using a
   Queue Index as defined above in <xref target="sec-di-qp"/>.  Multiple
   Queue Indexes MAY be present to allow for the case where same credit
   information applies to multiple queues. Multiple DA Credit Window
   Status Data Items are used to provide different queue-specific credit
   window information in one message. The special Queue Index value of
   255 is used to indicate that the Credit Window information applies to
   all queues.
</t>

<t>
  The format of the DA Credit Window Status Data Item is:
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | Data Item Type                | Length                        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                         Credit Window                         :
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   :                         Credit Window                         |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |  Queue Index  |               ...                             :
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   :                                ...            |  Queue Index  |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
  <list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Data Item Type:">TBA6</t>
    <t hangText="Length:">Variable
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      Per <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep"/> Length
      is the number of octets in the data item, excluding the Type and
      Length fields. It will equal 8 plus the number of Queue Index
      fields carried in the data item and MUST be at least 9.
    </t>
    <t hangText="Credit Window:"> 
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      A 64-bit unsigned integer, indicating
      the current number of credits, in octets, available for the
      router to send to the modem.  This is referred to as the
      Modem Receive Window in <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-manet-credit-window"/>. 
    </t>
    <t hangText="Queue Index:">
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      One or more 8-bit fields used to indicate a queue index defined by
      a Queue Parameters Data Item.  The special value of 255 indicates
      that the information in the data item applies to all queue indexes.
    </t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
  The receiving modem SHOULD check the received Credit Window value
  against the outstanding credits available at the time the last Credit
  Increment associated with the indicated MAC address and Queue Indexes
  were sent.  If the values significantly differ, i.e., greater than can
  be accounted for based on observed data frames, then the modem SHOULD
  send a Destination Update message carrying a DA Credit Grant data item
  to reset the associated Credit Window(s) to the data item indicated
  value.  Multiple values and queue indexes SHOULD be combined into a
  single Destination Update Control message when possible.
  Alternatively, and also in cases where there are small differences,
  the modem MAY adjust the values sent in DA Credit Grant data items to
  account for the reported Credit Window.
  </t>
</section>
<section anchor="sec-di-request" title="DiffServ Aware (DA) Credit Request">
<t>
   The DiffServ Aware, or DA, Credit Request Data Item data item is used
   by a router to request additional credits for a specific destination
   and Queue Index associated Credit window. DA Credit Request data
   items are carried in Credit Control messages, and only one DA Credit
   Request data item SHOULD be present in a message.
</t>
<t>
   Logical queues are identified using a Queue Index as defined above in
   <xref target="sec-di-qp"/>.  Multiple Queue Indexes MAY be present to
   allow for the case where the credit request applies to multiple
   queues.  The special Queue Index value of 255 is used to indicate
   that a credit request is being made across all queues.
</t>

<t>
  The format of the DA Credit Request Data Item is:
</t>
<t>
<figure>
<artwork>
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | Data Item Type                | Length                        |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |  Queue Index  |               ...                             :
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   :                                ...            |  Queue Index  |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
[LB note: a list of Queue Indexes is now supported as is special value
255.]
</t>
<t>
  <list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Data Item Type:">TBA7</t>
    <t hangText="Length:">Variable
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      Per <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep"/> Length
      is the number of octets in the data item, excluding the Type and
      Length fields. It will equal the number of Queue Index
      fields carried in the data item and MUST be at least 1.
    </t>
    <t hangText="Queue Index:">
      <vspace blankLines="1"/>
      One or more 8-bit fields used to indicate a queue index defined by
      a Queue Parameters Data Item.  The special value of 255 indicates
      that the request applies to all queue indexes.
    </t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
  A modem receiving this data item MUST provide a Credit Increment for
  the indicated MAC address and queue indexes via a DA Credit Grant
  carried in a new Credit Control Message. Multiple values and queue
  indexes SHOULD be combined into a single Credit Control message when
  possible.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section anchor="sec-compat" title="Compatibility">
<t>
  Sessions established with both peers identified as supporting the
  DiffServ Aware Credit Windowing Extension Type, see <xref
  target="sec-ext-type"/>, SHOULD NOT use the <xref
  target="I-D.ietf-manet-credit-window"/> defined Credit data items.
  If a node supporting the extension defined in this document, receives a
  <xref  target="I-D.ietf-manet-credit-window"/> defined data item, 
  the recipient MUST treat the received credit information as
  applying to Queue Index zero (0).
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="sec-sec" title="Security Considerations">
<t>
   The extension introduces a DiffServ awareness to the mechanisms
   defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-credit-window"/>.  The
   extension does not inherently introduce any additional threats above
   those documented in <xref target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep"/>.  The
   approach taken to Security in that document and <xref
   target="I-D.ietf-manet-credit-window"/> apply equally when running
   the extension defined in this document.
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="sec-iana" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>
  This document requests the assignment of 5 values by IANA.  All
  assignments are to registries defined by <xref
  target="I-D.ietf-manet-dlep"/>.
</t>
<section anchor="sec-iana-ext" title="Extension Type Value">
<t>
  This document requests 1 new assignment to the DLEP Extensions
  Registry named "Extension Tyoe Values" in the range with the
  "Specification Required" policy. The requested value is as follows:
</t>
<texttable anchor="table_et" title="Requested Extension Type Value">
  <preamble></preamble>
  <ttcol>Code</ttcol> <ttcol>Description</ttcol>
    <c>TBA1</c> <c>DiffServ Aware Credit Windowing</c> 
    <postamble></postamble>
    </texttable>
</section>
<section anchor="sec-iana-msg" title="Message Values">
<t>
  This document requests 2 new assignments to the DLEP Message Registry
  named "Message Values" in the range with the "Specification Required"
  policy. The requested values are as follows:
</t>
<texttable anchor="table_msg" title="Requested Message Values">
  <preamble></preamble>
  <ttcol>Type Code</ttcol> <ttcol>Description</ttcol>
    <c>TBA2</c> <c>Credit Control</c> 
    <c>TBA3</c> <c>Credit Control Response</c> 
    <postamble></postamble>
    </texttable>
</section>
<section anchor="sec-iana-di" title="Data Item Values">
<t>
  This document requests 4 new assignments to the DLEP Data Item
  Registry named "Data Item Values" in the range with the "Specification
  Required" policy. The requested values are as follows:
</t>
<texttable anchor="table_di" title="Requested Data Item Values">
  <preamble></preamble>
  <ttcol>Type Code</ttcol> <ttcol>Description</ttcol>
    <c>TBA4</c> <c>Queue Parameters</c> 
    <c>TBA5</c> <c>DA Credit Grant</c> 
    <c>TBA6</c> <c>DA Credit Window Status</c> 
    <c>TBA7</c> <c>DA Credit Request</c> 
    <postamble></postamble>
    </texttable>
</section>
</section>
</middle>

<?rfc needLines="20"?>
<back>
<references title="Normative References">

<?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-manet-dlep.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

</references>

<references title="Informative References">

<?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-manet-credit-window.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2474"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2475"?>

</references>
<?rfc needLines="100"?>
<!--
<section title="Acknowledgments">
   <t>
   </t>
   <vspace blankLines="100"/></t>
</section> 
-->
</back>
</rfc>

<!-- Local Variables: -->
<!-- fill-column:72 -->
<!-- End: -->
